[Music]
this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at e-r.
se radio is brought to you by the it computer society and by It software Magazine online at computer.org.
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering radio I'm your host Jeff dittle.
I'm excited to invite Jonathan Crossland as our guest on the show today.
Jonathan is a software architect computer programmer author and business owner.
he is the author of multiple books including beginning vb.net and professional vb.net.
he is currently working on a.
four- volume set called the programmer's handbook.
Jonathan is also the creator of the Amorous framework of design principles.
a philosophy and set of heris principles for designing software Solutions which is the topic of our show today. Jonathan welcome to the show.
hi Jeff thanks for inviting me.
yeah absolutely so I mentioned in the top of the show here the idea of the.
and I think I said it incorrectly so let me correct myself.
the immerse framework which is spelled am M RS e amerse and that's.
what we're here to talk about today.
so give our listeners a bit of a history and background on what this framework is sort of how it came to you and what it's for.
okay thanks Jeff so imerse is a set of values there are seven values it's a neonic.
and we'll get into those values.
the way it came about out is within the normal dealings and roles that you fulfill within software development.
talking to various stakeholders and getting to know different people you soon realize there's.
a disconnect there's a disconnect in terminology collaboration tools.
as you know in technology terms buzzword processes practices they're abounding right everywhere.
and it's all to solve this this collaboration problem.
and so at that time I thought perhaps there's something underneath all all of this right perhaps it's the software engineering me trying to see what underpins things.
so m is really the values the seven values that I came up with that I thought at the time and this is 20 years ago. that I thought would be.
underpinning everything that we collaborated on in these software roles and all the people.
so how did you arrive at 7.
okay so elimination right so generalization abstraction all the the usual software things that we've come to to know.
looking at personal values like trust and openness and mindfulness and being present and all these kinds of things.
and realizing wow that's that's personal.
looking at organizational values and and seeing that well this is virtue signaling this is doesn't really mean anything right.
they come up with words.
like vigilance and everyone in the organization wonders what what's that about like how do I be vigilant.
Vigilant about what right what what are we discussing here.
and so you when you look at those two angles to personal values it's a huge list right hundreds and hundreds of things.
and I the process came about by just saying well is this like this one is this in the same category.
does you know these are shapes so do these shapes Belong Together are they shapes is it an.
abstraction of shape what is it.
So eventually just boiled it down boiled down that's reachable.
okay so what things are reachable am I an approachable person okay so that falls into that category.
environmental sustainability that that falls there quite neatly what else Falls there.
and I wouldn't say I came up with the seven as they are now immediately but it's very close just by natural selection right.
just sort of pulling things apart and and grouping them.
okay so you mentioned values which I think is interesting.
because a lot of software companies as they think about process and they think about values they go back to the agile Manifesto.
which essentially is a statement of values it's a statement of we value these things over these other things.
and I believe if I'm recalling correctly there's four different things you know we value people and interactions over processes for example.
so I'm curious you know how much that influenced you and sort of where this exploration of values both maybe dovetails with that concept.
but also. maybe differs in some ways as well.
right so so immerse was kind of 1998 1999 was the first thought it popped into my head.
every other month when I saw the agile Manifesto came out I thought well do they value what I value.
and it largely aligned and I thought well that's gr because where I'm sitting right now it's it's not the same kind of values that I'm thinking we should have.
and so the agile Manifesto was kind of along the correct road right it it.
was to me at the time anyway it was something to to get behind because it understood some of the values.
but at that time I was still looking at it and saying well is that an axiom is that truth is that Universal can I generalize this even more.
but I think I didn't really click on it immediately it was really an evolution over the years.
where the axiology of of everything came more to the front and I really started looking at at the atoms of value.
right so the categorization the ontological approach.
and and then looking at the Adel Manifesto and saying well in this situation I agree with them in this situation perhaps not did they mean that.
and I think naturally people have put a lot more into the agile Manifesto than perhaps they originally put in.
and things evolve and people understand it differently 10 years later they understand it even better or or maybe in a different way.
and so I would say that it AED My Philosophy because I thought.
it was about values.
but even still today I think that the agile Manifesto is specialization in the context of people thinking about software and their everyday job.
right what they doing and the people that are around them.
where I feel that I zoomed out a lot more I zoomed out a lot more and try to get the bigger picture.
so so I think a m is underneath a merse those values the seven values you can use them to describe the agile Manifesto.
because if you favor.
people first then what is it well you're an approachable person right.
so you want to be approachable you want people to reach you and so there's various behaviors that come about from that value.
so I think it's to make it a shorter answer I would say it's it's very much in line but it's Underneath It All I think.
yeah and that's interesting too.
you talked about actually thinking through the values of the agile man Manifesto as opposed to just adopting them wholesale. and I think that's.
been a challenge for many organizations as well at least in my experience.
so you mentioned a moment ago the idea of virtue signaling which I think is really interesting when we talk about the idea of values.
and maybe you can speak to our listeners a little bit about your experience of why values actually matter.
I wonder if people maybe struggle like I think fundamentally we get that some sort of values drive us in this kind of thing.
but often it may seem to your point that.
maybe companies adopt values because they think they should.
but maybe they don't operate according to them or they don't really use them for anything that's effective.
so if can you speak to some of the reasons why in your experience it's important to consider our values and also how we operate according to them.
sure sure so when you think about values there there's sort of two lines of thought here.
some people get immediately taken by it because it's too personal or it's perhaps too abstract right. it's.
it's trust we understand trust we understand Integrity but what does it mean in business.
well it's ethical right we we're not talking about ethics right now we're talking about.
and so I think the discussion can very quickly get into a very personal area.
where people really don't feel comfortable discussing every Nuance about how open they may be for example.
who's going to say well I'm not honest you can't trust me.
so I think there's that personal level at first and and then there's the peer pressure.
the organizational the industrial psychologist the you know the sort of industrial complex of broadcasting your values.
who are you as a business you're why you're this you're that and and so on.
and then organizations have to sit down and say well is this something I want to do is it kooky am I talking about spirituality and ethics now.
what is values and if if it means something to the business what kind of words can I use that that describe us.
and I think people get lost.
in in both of those areas it's very very tough to sit down and say my business is we feel that these values are more important.
so what about that other value or that other one oh that's also important.
it's really really difficult because they're all important.
and I think there's there's those two starting points but I think it gets very complicated straight away when you bring everyone in.
now you've got different individuals with their value set not being able to fully describe their values all melting.
together to form the culture of the organization.
so I think values to to answer your first question I think values are so fundamental.
but I think it's flawed because the language is difficult the topic is tough it's very complicated.
and nobody really understands the pragmatism or you know it's not tangible that's that's the first side right.
the second side is I think people get caught up in in the direction of their company.
and perhaps one director or an owner may say well you know I I.
prefer openness and then the whole company will be about openness or you know it they'll pick something and go along those lines.
but I don't think it truly dives into the organization I think that's where everyone struggles.
how do we turn a culture around how do we influence a culture can we influence a culture should we influence.
so I think it's a very broad topic and I and and I think it's so complicated.
but mainly those two first points I think stop people from really identifying.
truth because it's confusing.
so immerse is about taking seven values that are not per personal they're about business.
but they have a personal category there is something personal about them that you can identify with.
but not feel like you're giving away your value so to speak.
and you can all gather around a certain pillar like reachable solvable extensible.
and you can sort of reach around it and say well I'm more extensible than I am minable.
and so but but not in a personal way interesting and.
we'll dive more into the specifics of of the values as we as we continue here.
so one thing you alluded to there which I think is fascinating is the distinction.
you didn't call it this but I'll summarize it as the distinction between stated values and actual values.
so share a little bit about how you've applied the immerse framework.
and how it can help sort of maybe resolve the possible tension between aligning stated values with actual values.
okay so you can very quickly see if somebody says.
well right we've got a support team and we want the phone to be picked up within three rings.
and we want to deal with that customer in a friendly way and immediately solve their problem.
if they can't I want it to be traveling to tier 2 and the phone must be picked up in in three rings.
if that is your your goal if that's what you're trying to achieve if that's where your vision is for your company for your support system.
you obviously put the customer.
first right you're obviously thinking about the customer you're obviously thinking about your impression that you give your customer.
and you're thinking of helping them.
so if you hire 19 20 year olds fresh out of uni or college or whatever.
they don't have a job they don't want to work it's their first entry point they think they're going to become a programmer one day.
so everyone's told them support you got to get into support it's a good maybe data capture but you'll get in there somewhere. and.
they're really not feeling it they're not understanding this their values are definitely not aligned with that kind of role.
so I think it's quite easy in that kind of example to to understand the difference between a youngster coming into business for the first time.
eager to G gain knowledge eager to do complex things or loan and and adapt.
but perhaps the customer service is not the first line of thought for him.
possibly it could be it could be their their hidden talent and they really want. to get in there.
but the point is does the value align with the role and the type of work and what the organization is promoting.
so if either one of those pillars are not aligned you're not going to fulfill what you're trying to achieve there.
and I think often the token value right is saying that you want to be customer focused.
but not understanding the culture and the people that you're employing to place them into these various roles.
means that it becomes something that's not enacted.
right or the training or the investment that it takes to take people to that level to that level.
correct correct there is a gap and and the Gap is what's important.
and immerses it's different layers of of a toolbox right different things for different situations.
but one of them is it's a language that you can look it's a mindset.
you've got these seven values and you can look at the gaps do I have a gap in in training this person they need to be more reachable.
this is the value that we need to instill what are the lessons we can employ to teach reachability.
and speaking of reachability let's start diving into the values of immerse.
and since this is a podcast and our listeners are only able to hear us and can't see.
I just want to describe briefly that first off we'll be going through these values not in their order in the word immerse.
there's actually multiple levels and you know I imagine that you can unpack for us a little bit.
more as we continue through the episode on why these levels exist and what it means to move through these levels.
so imagine a road and at the top we're going to start with a value that you just referred to called reachability which is at level one.
and we'll continue down through the seven values and describe what it means to move through the levels.
and a bit about how these values tend to interrelate with one another.
so let's first start with reachability. that's interesting because when I.
think values you know you mentioned before like trust or I love vigilance that's funny.
like so open to interpretation but I don't think of the word reachable as as a value.
so that's really interesting to me maybe unpack a little bit for for me and our listeners what is reachability.
and why is that the first level of value in this framework.
okay so the maturity index is what you alluded to.
so immerse has the seven values in the pneumonic and then it has the maturity index.
where it has these levels where it groups the values together to show you how mature you are right.
in terms of process or in terms of business model and so on.
so the reason why reachability is a value is because it easily encompasses being reachable.
reaching a goal in budget reaching a goal in time reaching a goal in skill.
so if you value somebody somebody's Talent OR somebody's hard work ethic and they are reachable to you.
and you combine to reach for a goal there is.
a value there so two people combine motivated to reach something.
so reachability is a value category that encompasses all those sorts of values.
that would make you collaborate with someone that will make you be open to reach a goal.
that will make you rely on a budget or understand what a budget is.
so it's all the things related to reaching for the goal and solvable.
which is also level one in the mature index I usually say it as reaching to solve.
and the reason why it's.
level one is because we as a business or as human beings we enjoy solving problems.
but you can't solve a problem with you know unlimited amount of time there has to be some time frame.
you reach to solve and your reaching is what.
well to maybe an academic in an institution it might be 2 years to NASA it may be 20 years to a small star up maybe six months.
how you reach and what you're reaching for so the value category encompasses just keep in mind.
it always encompasses a whole set of values.
that people who are reachable and approachable in that way would Encompass.
and so I do have a list of these values which I haven't published yet.
but I'm it's it's in a matter of like process elimination and research really.
I intend to deliver surveys and see and and sort of plot more value into these categories.
I have a fair idea what should be there but over time I'd like to establish them scientifically and see that they fall into.
these categories.
so why reachability first I maybe it's obvious but explore a little bit more you know in your thought process on how you arrived at that.
and and I appreciate the clarification that reachability is a category of of multiple values so it's an interesting way of looking at it.
so that's a helpful clarification there but but why why reach a ility first.
why is that the the first step in in this process of organizational maturity.
so if you if you start a business you will.
first start with what is it that you want to provide is it a service is it a product.
did you stumble on a solution and now you need to reach people and give it to them.
the reason why reach is first is because it's not always a solution.
and then we try and reach sometimes you know you're going to start a business and you're going to reach.
and you need to discover who you're going to reach and what budget you have to reach those people or.
that market and so on.
so reachable on a small level or a large level it has to be something that makes sense.
whether it's an ad hoc coder or a small startup or a corporate.
so the reason why reachable is first is because it's not always the solution that comes first.
you're reaching to solve or you're reaching somebody to give them a solution but that's never clear.
so I chose reachable and solvable to be level one so really they jointly level one and all the values.
are interdependent right they have these relationships together.
although reachability is first it's it's first with solvable and I think it's very very coupled.
but it is separate enough for us to know and understand am I solving a solution right now or am I reaching to solve a solution.
and I think there's a difference in how we approach that.
somebody might be reaching continuously to get you know nuclear sorted out for energy or make it more efficient or do something like that.
it could be a long-term.
goal you're just reaching for something you're not sure of what the solutions are you're not sure of all the problems.
but you're going to reach and you hope it's solvable that's the idea or you wouldn't. it's solvable correct but we're not sure yet.
exact or we're not sure how it will be solvable.
yeah correct so if you have a solution first fair enough you have a solution.
but is is it a valid solution for a valid problem and will it fit in an environment. so there's.
there's a lot of other values that will now come into play.
and so I chose reachable because I thought that is the first thing whether you've got a solution or not you're reaching.
okay so level one to sum up is we're reaching for a solution we may have one.
and we're figuring out how to get it out in the market make make people aware we're you know we're reaching out into the market.
or we're reaching for a solution and trying to discover perhaps a solution and.
then it sounds too you mentioned that these are organizational values but there's a there's a personal aspect of this as well.
so am I reachable as a person it sounds like that's another another way of looking at this.
so how would an organization you know how how would I as a business owner use this to help reach this this first level.
of to you sorry to overload the term to achieve this first level.
like what what does it look like when I've achieved this first level.
of of maturity with reachability and and solvability right.
yeah just just to to knock a point home before I answer that.
and that is immerse is a language where you have the benefit of using all the same terminologies across any Department right any person.
and so there is a a ambiguity there sometimes or you may feel that there is.
because am I talking of this now in a personal capacity or or so on.
but the categories that I've come up with here with these values I've.
really thought hard about whether the personal and the organization would align.
so reachable is really whether it's what you feel is a personal value it still aligns very much for the organizational equivalent.
so reachable what it looks like is that if you're looking at code you could see this.
if you're a coder you could you could see this I hope the analogy would help it is software engineering of course so I expect it to hit home.
but if if you take a code base where somebody.
has tried to solve a problem it kind of has a different feel a look about it.
than to somebody who's already established how to solve the problem and has thought about it and elegantly executed.
you know that code that you've got that's commented out and you Wen to sure and you you know I'll leave it there for the moment.
and you've refactored and you've changed things and you try it again and you've ran it and you've debugged it.
and that's what an organization looks like it.
feels that way it is that way because all they've worried about all they've been concerned of is reaching the goal.
and in that you've got no time to faf around with anything else.
is there a meta problem don't worry about it now can we do this well.
I'm not sure forget about we're trying to solve this problem remember this is the problem.
and so an organization just like our code will mirror and reflect those two values.
because those two values are what we've been aing for.
and so in an organizational field you might find processes that are ad hoc.
uh lack of process maturity nothing embedded people are just doing all sorts of things to accomplish things there's nothing set in stone.
you may find that there are one or two solutions that are not compatible with each other they sort of cross purpose.
maybe the solution is not all-encompassing perhaps the solution doesn't cover all the bases.
and so so maybe you're late with deadlines possibly the budget is too small and then you.
have to reiterate and do a next iteration.
you will see characteristics of just reaching and solving you you will see it a mile away.
and we we can call that a prototype it will feel like a prototype it will be a prototype.
if I'm inventing something it will have cardboard and sticky tape and everything else holding it together and it won't be a product.
so I think ritual and solvable if you think of it from that point of view you can see it. now obviously that's.
subjective I'm giving you examples of this and in every context it's a bit different.
and the first level of immerse is really to understand for yourself what these values mean in your context.
and it may be slightly different that's the whole point right of values and we'll get into weights I'm sure.
but reachable I could reach for something but only be 50% a part of that that reachability.
it's only 50% of my efforts are going into that it's not a 100%. uh solvable is 100% you.
know for example so it doesn't have to be a binary thing right.
so I'm going to briefly jump to the end but I don't want to get too deep into it now.
because I want to work through these a bit more linearly.
but maybe talk a little bit about what happens if say you're in a context where the the goal of the business is to reach a solution.
so we're aiming for level one.
but we have people on our team who are really really excited about.
values that are further down say agility or extensibility which again we'll dig into more in a minute.
but speak to that a little bit now we're going to get to those and we'll dive into them a little bit more later.
but I want to highlight that now so listeners see where we're going as well.
and and here's here's specifically why I think what you just described is what a lot of people think agility means.
and yet in the immerse framework agility comes much later down in.
the maturity model so speak to that a little bit for now we'll dig into it a little bit more as we go through the levels.
but what happens and and then how do we deal with it.
maybe if we're in a situation where there are conflicting values.
and maybe from this framework values that require more maturity are attempt there's an attempt to apply them.
when maybe that's not really what we're aiming for yet as an organization.
right so I think the reason why agility is not.
part of reaching and solvable and why the agile movement May regard reachable and solvable as part of agility or so almost entirely.
is that when you're reaching to solve you're going to communicate a lot.
you're going to get short feedback and you're going to build that prototype.
now in some organizations that may be enough and it's all about context that may be enough.
you reaching towards a solution every day you're having your meeting you're discussing a problem you work at it you solve it you deploy.
it and off you go reaching and solving.
that doesn't inherently mean that you're paying attention to any of the other values that come about.
such as am I is this fit for purpose am I building something skew right.
I'm going off on a tangent am I over engineering under engineering.
there's so many other things to worry about that reaching and solving.
if that's all you feel that agility is I I think agility is more.
but if that's all you feel that it is then you're very.
much mistaken.
and also if agility is implemented within reachable and solvable.
so in other words now I'm also trying to adapt to agility.
what of all the other things like just neatness tidy maintainability of my code base.
can I roll out my code to another region.
Well it can't even deal with this new date format right.
but here I am expressing an entirely new process that the team is going to go through we're going to do cicd.
but the code base is not even you know.
ready so I think the reason why mine is agility we'll talk later about it but agility to me is something else.
it's an add-on to reachable and solvable.
so we've covered level one with reachable and solvable and then we start moving into level two.
so describe for our listeners what are we after with level two like what's the goal.
and then in this case there are there are three categories of values that we can kind of walk through in in level two of this maturity model.
sure so you know they're very com very many competing methodologies on how we accomplish something whether that's in software or anything else.
if you reach to solve and you reach to solve and you're building what I am imagining to to be valuable but.
quick.
in one organization it may not be adequate you need checklists you need some level of quality and so on.
if you're going to add that to level one in terms of the process with the mindset of reaching and solvable. you may not.
be looking at these other values that I've got in level three.
so that that's why they're now level three to get your attention and say right level three is important you've been reaching and solving.
but what do you now need to do the three values there are minimal environmental and maintainable.
and so it's obvious if you think of a bit of code you've written some code you think it's the solution.
now you understand the problem now it's time to make that a bit more minimal. now.
it's time to think about maintainability how how am I going to maintain this later.
now's the time to think about the environmental consequence.
such as oh that's Java it's not JavaScript right.
okay oh hang on I'm going to have to migrate this now because it's actually in the web context.
you know i' I've been sitting in the wrong environment.
so so whatever it may be you know you got to look at those three values and add it to the reachable and solvable. because what you're trying.
to do is make something longlasting you're trying to make something that not only solves the problem that you set out to solve.
but solves it fit for purpose solves it elegantly solves in a way that can be maintained.
so that next year it's still solving the same problem.
or perhaps environmentally when you release it it solves the problem for that environment or another environment and so on.
so the contexts are important and that reminds me of it works on my machine right. so you've built something.
reachable and solvable it works on my machine right.
you commit it everyone has a honia because is not neat it's not maintainable you have put no thought into this. so what's going to happen is it's going to be rejected.
and you're going to have to spend some time making more maintainable a little bit more fitful purpose.
you're going to have to think it through make it solve meta problems as well.
because you've just introduced a whole batch of those think about the environment you weren't using.
the same code language whatever right.
so you have to think about those three things and and that gives you that maturity.
if you take a a solution that you've got and it's a bunch of sticks you know sewn together and there it is.
that's one level of solution and the next level is improving that and making sure that it's fit for purpose now fit for the environment.
so is there a risk in waiting to think about maintainability until Level Two For example. oh okay well of.
talk a little more about that.
well it may or may not be depending on the context and and that's why a m makes no judgment call.
and it's not a framework for saying to you you must follow these levels right.
it's a level of maturity where the usefulness is to inspect what you have and say what do I have here.
what values have I been implementing or adding to the system and.
it's a mirror it's a reflection.
and then you can see the maturity. but if.
if you if you have a good team and everyone's pretty good at their jobs and you've got good budgets you're well established good client customer base.
you might say we aim for level two immediately with absolutely everything we do.
and I'll give you a little analogy if you take test driven development it's reachable and solvable what they do is they reach they write a test.
and then they solve that and then they iterate and they reach and they solve and they reach and they solve and.
then they need to refactor and refactor is considered a positive term in this regard.
that you're now positively refactoring and therefore you iteratively improving the test and the code.
and so therefore what are you doing you're adding minimal maintainability and environmental factors to that test and to that code base iteratively making it better.
so tdd in in essence is reachable solvable first as a process and secondly adding level two.
so I just brought that analogy in because it's it's a coding podcast after all.
absolutely and.
I think that's a helpful clarification there and also you know you you definitely helped refine the word refactor.
which usually just means rework.
but in this case you're saying let's take something that works let's improve it by making it maintainable making it minable.
and considering these environmental factors.
so and as you said there are there are risks to just being reachable solvable.
and you know if you're just reachable solvable that analogy seems to imply maybe it solves the problem but it's a mess nobody can understand. it.
my favorite example there is you get blame later and you discover that it was actually you that wrote that horrible know awful code.
so maybe you should make it maintainable to help to help you.
something else I appreciate that you clarified is one way to sum this up is.
it sounds like you're saying that this framework is more descriptive in some ways than prescriptive.
you can use it to help come up with prescriptions but but it's more helping you describe how are we operating. and.
then possibly use it to consider how could we operate is that a fair assessment.
correct so the immerses is a value system.
and in that sense of the word as in complex system or or systems thinking.
and the idea is is that we're we're not in a linear anything right.
we don't have a road map which is not a map or or a road which road are we on now.
which team is on which road going in which direction values is is more helpful because we.
can look at a system and.
say what is the current state of the system.
we can ask good questions we can use a m to come up with a set of questions relating to that category and ask it of the system.
are we we reachable do we have enough budget is there enough time are we placing efforts into minimal.
are we placing efforts in maintainability where is our agility right.
is it everywhere is it do we need to apply agility in every area is it a.
mindset that the whole company must do or is it just a part of the code base that needs to be agile.
right because we're going to different territories.
is it aligned with the fact that our business is going into different territories so the code base needs to be a mirror on that strategy right.
so if we're reachable our code needs to be reachable if we're agile our code needs to be agile.
and so yes it's very much a reflection a mirror to check the current state.
and then in immerse I've got the good old Gap analysis right so where do we want to go right is this ideal like where is our our ideal.
and it's not about saying well there's an objective we're marching on a road to get there.
it's more that what do we tweak what value do we tweak in our system that will align us or move us in that direction.
so level one we're reaching for a solution and level two we're tidying it up we're we're fit and.
finish right we're making it as you said maintainable environmental and minimal.
and we'll get to level three in just a moment.
but explain a little bit more about you know you mentioned before these are value categories they're groupings of values.
so what are some of the values that you would say fit within each of these three categories.
so for example you know what does it mean in your mind to be maintainable specifically.
so maintainable is something where you can go to something and improve it or.
ensure that it remains in its same state right.
so naturally entropy and all sorts of things kick in.
and maintain ility is maintaining the standard or maintaining the level in which you set.
and that could be at any level that you set it's just that your mindset is am I thinking about maintainability right.
so the values oriented around that would be diligence discipline right wax on wax off right.
so it's that kind of idea.
and if you place somebody with those kind of values somebody who.
you you've learned that their Hobby is let's say old cars antique vehicles.
and every weekend they're out there buffing and cleaning and they're meticulous.
well they're probably a candidate because their values align with maintaining historical value and keeping it up to date.
and you can see that personal value reflecting in what people do.
and therefore you can say well you're the perfect guy to manage the maintainability of this code base make shine right.
and you're probably giving it to the right.
person exactly. yeah minimal is. each of these categories is also um an entry point a doorway to a process or a framework.
so imagine the reachable framework which is all about reaching that's all it's about.
and you can you can Orient your entire business around that and has processes and it has things that you've built on being reachable.
or level three which is agile we'll start in a minute you can build an agile methodology all around being agile.
and so each of these value systems lends itself into that whole world.
so you you you asked a question which made me say that now and I can't remember what you said.
but I think each value it's very important to understand that it's how you prescribe what you want to do with those values right.
so if you are agile focused then you can use an agile methodology.
so you've explored a little bit about maintainability.
let's talk a little bit more about minimal and environmental.
and what are the what are the values that you would see there.
and maybe.
as you said you could have a methodology for each of these particular I should correct myself value categories.
so what is environmental specifically mean in this level two of maturity.
so environmental is is something where you're going to say well we care about things aligning in the world.
we care about sustainability in terms of a software design pattern you would care about the adapter pattern.
because everyone can adapt to the same thing you care about polymorphism you care about things that align with that concept you.
care about neatness of code conventions because you're environmentally friendly.
you don't want some you don't want to design something and have someone break the design throw it out the water right.
not implement the right.
interface throw it in the wrong place then they're not adhering to the environment.
somebody who's environmentally focused will really really take care of the ecosystem that's already there.
and will expand on that ecosystem in very good ways they will be sensitive to it those kind of values that you have.
and yes.
they are personal values and you can think about that just sustainability.
somebody who's diligent about recycling is probably somebody who cares about the environment.
which is probably somebody who cares about coding conventions look it's a leap right but that's the sort of idea the thread that you can follow.
maybe another example for environmental might be creating Dev containers so that everybody has a consistent devel development environment.
correct absolutely.
and if I was to build a methodology around minimal I would probably create lean right because that's.
what it's about minimal it's it's about reducing waste.
it's about making something just right fit for purpose.
getting rid of all the fluff getting rid of all the things that don't matter building it to its core.
and that's something that that the lean has.
so I think each one of these and remember it's weights right we can it's not not that we have to fall in one camp.
and I think if there's any motivation behind imerse it is to explain to people that you and I.
value different things and we can still work together and we don't have to be dogmatic.
it occurs to me as well that we could apply this not just to coding and not just to our business.
but it appears that we could apply this to how we do software architecture thoughts on that.
well on on the website I've got a a software architecture post which talks about how we can use that.
and so there many sort of problems that we have in software architecture right tradeoffs we.
have to understand which solution is going to work out the best in the scenario.
and it's temporal so over time our best solution today is not the best solution then.
and we've got to play that game we've got to understand what is the tradeoff we're making now.
and is have an impact if force a and force B come into light next year should we build scalability into now.
and so we still kind of want to do the immerse maturity with architecture what we'd like to do.
is we'd like to say what is the problem we're trying to solve here and how are we going to reach it.
we got to look at our developers and say are they good at that can they do this have we done microservices before.
do we you know have a department that does deployments what is it that we've got here.
how much agility do we want to build into the system is an extensible we'll get to level 3.1.
is it extensibility that we're after is it an. ecosystem.
and so our software architecture is tailored towards the weights that we would apply to these values.
and getting it right is is difficult like it always is.
but I feel that a merse and by the way a m one of the first the early incarnations of it was I had the problem solution statement.
it's very much like the architectural design records that they have now.
the problem was you write it down this is the problem that we're trying to solve the solution this is the.
solution and then you put your weights down for your solution.
so your weights for each value where were just trying to reach and solve this zeros for all the rest.
like that was the thing.
and when you look at it a year later and you look at it you can tell straight away.
they weren't imp they weren't implementing agility or extensibility here it just needed to be done they had to do that.
and it was was a nice reminder or at least a love letter from.
the architect to your future developer or self as to why you did something and why it was chosen.
often that's completely gone right you don't understand.
I I've seen many things I've done I'm going why did I do that there must have been a reason it's so stupid right.
why did I do that and learn hack and then describe them quite quite right.
yeah so so I used to use a merse in that respect to kind of give myself a hint as to what the values.
were what were the things that I was most concerned about at that moment.
interesting and then you could come back later as you mature and decide that you know.
we've built this this solution that is becoming unmaintainable.
and it is not as minimal as possible.
and it is not considering you know some of these environmental factors of ease of understanding ease of portability or whatever these things might be.
and you can start to move in the direction that you that you that you want to go.
so that's levels one and two so we've got we're we're aiming to reach a solution we're now tidying it up.
and now we get to level three and this is where you recommend that we begin.
I don't know if you recommend this is where the framework says that we've reached a level of maturity.
where agility is now something to consider.
which again I think might be a question listeners might have is we should be AG from the start.
so talk a little bit about what it.
means that in your mind and again you didn't say you know you have to do these one at a time.
it's a way of looking at what you are doing and comparing it with where you want to be.
but clarify a little bit why in your mind agility is a is a level three of maturity.
and not a level one or a level two.
okay so the traditional agile I can say traditional alcoh it's 20 odd years right.
I mean yeah it's been around for a. while it's been around.
so what you need to do here is you need to iterate and you need to have constant feedback.
and what you find in the field is that customers don't know what they want that's a common thing.
customers want something and then want something else.
projects are being outsourced and the customer or the stakeholder wants a fixed something.
they're not happy to just let it run on and on and on 3 weeks 5 weeks when are we finishing is there a deadline. well.
I can give you I can install now it doesn't have the PDF I wanted right.
that's the conversations that you have people want fixed costs or at least they want to understand the ballpark.
so you've got that kind of scenario in the real world.
and you've got this kind of method saying well it's okay let's just communicate together a lot more.
and you can get somebody this perhaps is more XP than it is agile although lines are blured.
bring your customer and let them sit in.
our team let them see what we're doing and participate let's give daily releases.
so you can see in 20 odd years of doing this sort of thing it's happen maybe twice that a customer looks at that release and gives feedback.
they're not around when you want them to be.
they they they say something in a meeting and you say well why didn't you bring that up three months ago.
there's so much of that going on what do we do do we educate our customers to be.
agile our Technologies to be agile our people our mindsets our everything.
so the only reason why agile will succeed 100 is if everyone is agile everyone.
well that's the real world is that people are going to be something upfront something this something that they'll have an expectation.
they'll demand something stakeholder will demand he might be old fashioned this is the real world.
we've got people with different understandings and different values.
so in a in a setting where every single person is behaving according to the agile.
short iterations helping you short feedback everything's swimming sure great.
but does everyone have that environment and is it good for everyone to adopt that I don't know.
well is it that's I mean let's let's talk about that a little bit.
because we see across the industry you mentioned before virtue signaling.
and it seems in my experience you tell me if yours is similar that a lot of times the word agile is virtue signaling.
it's we're doing the ceremonies we're doing these things we're following these and.
to your point maybe it's maybe it's not really working for you.
and that's one of the thing that intrigues me about this imerse framework is is it can perhaps.
you you even mentioned earlier when you first read the manifesto what you did is you you deconstructed and you thought about it.
you didn't just say well let's let's go with this this sounds good.
so so speak because I'm sure to some you know some of our listeners might feel this is controversial.
thinking well we're doing agile.
and it's working great and whatever.
but is it how do you evaluate that how do you determine whether or not you actually have agility.
as opposed to practicing ceremonies that have the word agile you know sort of bolted onto them.
so we like adding a positive or A negative to something and we're biased we We'll add a positive if we think it's good and we enjoy it.
take refactoring refactoring is neutral refactoring is re factoring I.
previously factored now I'm going to refactor. what is inherent.
in the word refactor is only one thing that's change.
if I'm refactoring I'm changing that is it that is inherent I'm changing for the good or the bad who knows right.
if a whole team of people say you don't tell me to refactor I'm a professional I'll refactor right.
I'll refactor nobody can stop me from refactoring it's part of my job.
you've probably heard that sort of thing going around right it's a very arrogant view.
what they're effectively saying is I will make a subjective call.
as to whether that code is correct or not and modify it subjectively inducing change into the system.
and I'll do it if I want to that's a very very bad bias.
refactoring is neutral but people if you ask out there they'll instinctively think and attribute it to a positive action refactoring is positive.
controversially I think refactoring is a code smell.
because I think whenever I see refactoring going on the questions the alarm bells that go off the smells that I get is why did we not.
finish that is that not done I thought it was done are you changing the tests as well.
are you doing this do we have to get our customers to approve it again what what's going on here.
so I don't see it automatic Bally as a positive I see it as an action of change.
and then I'm thinking well do we have processes involved to deal with that change now.
really it's change refactoring is change inherently do we have change management in place. so we're really talking.
about here the question is is it the right.
time for agile.
well if I don't have change management but I've got the philosophy of refactoring it will then you know it's at the right.
time.
so change management goes together with tdd we might say well we test and now that helps us minimize change.
but does it does it minimize all change it's not all change.
what about documentation change what about getting the user to understand the change there many many things that it would change. so.
I don't I don't feel like people are looking at things from a value system and.
saying I value refactoring it's positive to me it's my value.
okay is it a value of the system does the system require tons of change.
and agile all the processes is to embrace change and deal with change but all the practices make change.
so let's think about that that's a fascinating a self fulfilling prophecy.
I will refactor where I want induced change but I need change management I'll do tdd to.
handle that we'll do cic I'll give change to my customers immediately via a pipeline change change change.
right when is that going to end is there a cliff is it get does it get faster and faster.
okay so I feel I feel that agility is part of our answer we need to get feedback we need to talk to customers.
we need to do things in smaller bite chunks and not bite off too much.
we we need to do things like that we need immediate feedback but.
we also need long-term feedback signals right we also need stability.
we also need to understand when change is good and when it's not good.
and so I've put agile level three because I feel it's the best time value-wise.
and it's no judgment just the value-wise now that I've I've reached and solved something.
and I've reached it and and all's good and I've made it a bit more minimal and and made a bit more elegant.
and I've looked at maintain and it's a bit stable now it.
it it runs in different environments in the environments at least that I wanted to run in.
and when a new developer comes he picks up on it with the coding guidelines he understands it it's got right amount of documentation.
okay guys we're ready to go into the next territory how can we make this codebase more agile now.
right it's probably the best time.
Tiding what you've done is an important concept.
so if your garden you've had a a nice party the garden is spewed with all.
sorts of things beer cans everything lying in the garden if you're that way inclined right there it is.
you say right today is the day that I clean the hedges mow the grass and do everything.
it's probably time to clean first right probably have to tidy up everything.
and then you know if if it's too late and the sun's gone down schedule another day to do the mowing you can't do everything at once.
and and you have to pick the right. moments.
so to me level.
three the reason why you may have more success with agility and with being agile and having pipelines and doing test driven and all those sorts things.
is perhaps the code base is mature it's neat and so on or perhaps it's fresh it's green field.
and you can start it all and you've got the budget and people have given you plenty of time to reach that.
but that's not indicative of all contexts so therefore it can't be the answer for all contexts.
and if I start you.
know draw a a line and put on the one end ad hoc coder working from home office by himself for One customer.
and all on the other side software engineering checklists regulations the best practices we can adopt constantly improving.
if I take refactoring or tdd or anything where am I going to put it on the line.
is going to be where the most positive the most negative is.
and as I shift it around the positives and negatives are going to change if I got three people.
people if I'm in this environment or that environment.
and I think the bias is really thinking that there is one fits all.
but that practice fits all that methodology fits all.
and I think it's an evolutionary thing.
another reason why ERS is around in my opinion why why I think it's heartfelt Le right.
why I think people should look at it and and think about it more is to think about where their solution fits.
is it this is it that value is is it more of.
this value and and then look at their context and adjudicate where it is and which methodology would align.
we can't all go to AWS there's got to be other hosting platforms doing other things right.
we're not all going to live in one place and sometimes an on premise solution is still the right.
solution versus a distributed Cloud solution.
correct but but look at us we dived right in right we dived right in and we tend to do that yeah.
I think it's interesting too when we.
talk about maturity you know is is we can consider you know agility and the agile Manifesto.
it was created by a group of individuals who each had I believe at least 20 years of experience in the industry at the time.
now they all have over 40 years of experience each in the industry.
and they were talking about how they work together.
so talk about maturity you've been in the industry for 20 years.
and if you've been in the industry for 20 years especially that you know.
the people that we're talking about here that that were a part of that group they were talking about how they work.
and if we apply that to a brand new team what's been your experience with that kind of approach.
perhaps trying to apply principles that were created by individuals with a lot of experience now being brought to bear on a say brand new development team.
for sure my eyes weren't always open in this regard.
I've started a project five devs on my team I had a.
software house I've got people we're going to build this this is what I'd like to build.
go and contact these customers see if they want to buy into this no we don't have anything yet it doesn't matter go and talk to them.
go and see what they want you start on a template get it going right just start something.
we're going to just iterate and just get something going three weeks from now I'm going to set up a meeting little mini conference we'll invite some people.
in that industry to see if they want to join forces doesn't work well at least it didn't for Me Maybe it works for somebody else.
the reason why it didn't work for me is customers came with well what have you got to show me.
oh I've already got this and this does yours do those things.
oh great I can write that down but I'm eight months away from implementing that because I don't have these other things.
so it's useful it's useful it's good but it doesn't.
always work the conditions have to be right.
and so I think whether it's Greenfield or not I think a lot of people get caught up as you said the the am authors are in an environment.
you know people who have written books well established worked at all sorts of large companies being asked questions important questions.
how do we roll this out to a customer well how many users you have 100,000.
okay well is that the same answer to if you've got five partners and there's only.
25 users across those five partners and you're very established but it's not a big deal it's not a big scat system it's a monolith it works.
are you going to think in the same way way.
and and the unfortunate thing is that there are probably a 100,000 development teams like that that go microservices and off they went.
modifying their code moving it changing it getting it to something else.
and it's just another incarnation of the same thing a tradeoff new problems instead of the old problems.
and I've been in this game long enough and I'm sure you have as well.
yet another class named user yet another class named whatever you know you see it again and again.
and you may get a new framework that you install and it's a different set of problems.
and people are hopping from one framework to another just inheriting different problems.
and now we reached level 3.1 which is extensive another controversial one I think.
yes so so again I can imagine someone saying well we want extensibility.
from the start why would you put that that so far down in the levels of maturity.
but what happens when again people try to jump straight to this and maybe ignore the previous sets of values.
and what does it mean in your mind to be extensible and how do how do teams achieve it and how does a m help them achieve it.
so I think I think if you if we first take a business analogy and we say right we have a business model and we're.
starting out small we're going to solve that problem we've got a small customer base.
and we we try and improve it for them.
and then we become agile and we want to modify some things and satisfy them in short spurts.
get something they've requested make them happy right off they go.
extensibility is is basically agility level three is agile.
level 3.1 is extensibility so it's only a point one change it's it's an important one.
what you're doing now is you're codifying whether that's in process mindset.
values or code you're codifying what it means that agility.
what it means that agility in terms of plugin ability.
so it's no more just about being adaptive We Now understand how to be adaptive in this area.
and this area of being adaptive requires these sorts of interfaces and plugins and we will create those plugins.
we now know we need to integrate with that API or those things we can build them.
and so it's not it's not just good enough and I think this is where agility.
in the controversial bit is I think the agile movement has one more step to go.
that's turning themselves into extensibility.
and that's when we come of age when we understand the difference between design time agility and runtime agility.
in that sense where we're actually building and planning ahead to build an ecosystem that parts are modular.
that pieces get plugged in and they just work you don't have to recompile the Beast right.
so I think it's a minor step up but I think extensibility is the maturity.
that you now get from understanding the previous levels.
and to answer your question no I don't prescribe that you don't have to start at extensive.
you can if you if you've got backing from a venture capital firm and you're going to take on Google Docs and Google Docs.
or any other platform has an ecosystem ecosystem the plugins and so on.
they've got a very very big developer Community you know straight away that that has to be part of your strategy.
are you going to emergently design.
a plug-in system probably not.
are you going to eventually get to a plugin system probably not.
but extensibility is a much higher level of complexity it requires more effort.
it's in on the one hand over engineering if you don't need an ecosystem.
so that's why it's right at the end 3.1.
you have to be agile in what you do in order to be extensible if you're not there's a miscommunication or a misalignment of values.
imagine you've got an ecosystem with plugins and somebody contacts you.
and says I really need a plugin to do X.
and you can your answer is well I can't do that why would you say you can't do that.
surely your agility is at the right.
level for your extensibility it goes hand in hand.
surely by doing plugin you have a minimal and maintainable system that you can support the plugins.
because if you're not ready with all of that and you just build an extensibility what you're going to do.
and what's going to happen is and you'll. see it translate in teams our API has changed oh everything's broken right.
this happens again and again and again when you're not ready you don't have change management in place.
you don't have versioning of your apis in place.
you don't have different customers on different versions of the API some proprietary.
you can't do that you can't fit it in you can't build for it you can't scale with it.
and so you're not ready for extensibility.
so you can introduce it right in the get-go but you're.
going to pay that price takes a long time to get there yeah.
correct and in some it sounds like that's essentially a lot of what aers is about.
is identifying the tradeoffs between values that may be competing.
and if we if we value everything at once we don't really it's like have you know everything's the first priority.
well then nothing's the first priority correct.
and so this is giving us a way to Think Through what our actual priorities currently are.
and then perhaps think about if.
we want them to be different how can we start to do that Gap analysis and move from our current state to to where we want to be.
and all in the context of as you mentioned change management and how we organize to achieve business objectives.
so I think just sort of to wrap it together because it's it seems logical.
and that is immerse the different layers that you can apply is immerse is itself using itself.
so if you want to use a merse at level one.
all you need to do is follow the first two principles reachable and solve.
now how do you reach a merse and solve with a merse well all you really got to do is get to know the values and talk about it.
that's all you got to do people inside a team just has to start using the language and getting familiar with saying.
that's unreachable solving that problem introduces more problems I cannot handle the additional meta problems right now.
we haven't maintained the last set of features.
that we've built in the last 6 months it hasn't got to a maintainable level yet.
so level one really is just understanding and using the language.
but if you look on the website and most other or you'll see that there's so many layers that you can then add on.
and use it as weights and collaboration systems and and everything else.
well that's a great wrapup.
so if people want to find out more about what you're up to where do you recommend they go. so I'm starting.
a YouTube channel I've got one subscriber and that's me.
and it's a very dangerous uh uh thing to start right.
because nowadays you have to make a video one per day or more to really get it promoted.
but that's not the post purpose of it the purpose is to just convey the ideas of immerse small item by small item.
so if people are interested they can search for immerse am M RS e on YouTube.
go to the immerse do org website and see the link and.
then just sort of learn about it.
and the nice thing about imerse is that it fits within everything because it underpins everything.
so whether you you know you don't have to give up anything you don't have to reject anything else.
you just have to understand why you accept certain things and why you reject other things.
and understand your values and your team's values.
well Jonathan thank you so much for joining me today it's been an absolute pleasure.
thanks Jeff this is Jeff dittle for software engineering.
radio thanks for listening.
thanks for listening to SC radio an educational program brought to you by It software magazine.
for more about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at se- radio.net.
to provide feedback you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter.
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team e-r.
this and all other episodes of SC radio is licensed under creative comments license 2.5. thanks for.
[Music]